# Jingxiao Chen

+1 (616) 920-4055 ♦ Jingxiao.chen@uth.tmc.edu ♦ http://www.jingxiaochen.com Google Scholar: https://bit.ly/2EBdMHI ♦ LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/jingxiao-chen/

# **Summary**

Ph.D. student trained in biostatistics, with strong programming, statistics and communication skills developed from extensive research experience and ability independently or as part of a team. Special expertise in the following areas:

- **Statistics**
- Machine Learning
- Deep Learning
- Statistical Modeling

- **Data Visualization**
- Data Cleaning and Wrangling
- Data Mining
- **Data Analytics**

#### Education

**University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston Ph.D.,** Biostatistics Anticipated in May 2023 **Case Western Reserve University** M.S., Biostatistics **Purdue University B.S.**, Mathematical Statistics

# **Professional Experience**

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston

August 2020 – Present Houston, TX

Houston, TX

Cleveland, OH

West Lafayette, IN

January 2018

May 2016

- Developing machine learning models that improve the prediction accuracy of the prognosis of traumatic brain injury using patient admission demographic data and clinical characteristics with supervised learning algorithms
- Performing statistical analysis with the unstructured data monitoring the trend of daily and weekly SARS-CoV-2 infections in Greater Houston to inform public health policy
- Visualizing spatial distribution data with geographical maps by time series
- Generating reproducible summary reports with new data using Sweave on a weekly basis

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

August 2018 – July 2020

MD Anderson Cancer Center

Houston, TX

Conducted methodological research on unsupervised clustering and classification on high dimensional single-cell RNA sequencing (scRNA-seq) data

- Deployed survival analysis and time-dependent AUC (Receiver Operator Characteristics analysis) using clinical characteristics (i.e. tumor subtype & pathological stage) to validated tumor transcriptome decomposition results
- Established tumor transcriptome deconvolution analysis pipeline to understand the tumor microenvironment (TME) using available gene expression cancer consortium such as the Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) projects
- Built LFSPRO, an R package for TP53 germline mutation carrier estimation, and cancer risk predictions which outperformed typical clinical diagnostic criteria
- Benchmarked deconvolution methods utilize cell-type-specific gene expression from scRNAseq data to characterize cell type compositions from bulk RNA-seq data in complex tissues
- Prepared manuscripts for grants and publication in peer-reviewed journals

**Biostatistician** *Cleveland Clinic* 

July 2017 - July 2018

Cleveland, OH

 Performed feature selection, multiple regression, tree-based methods and regularization regression to examine the risk factors of patients undergoing elective posterior lumbar decompression

- Provided statistical consulting for other researchers and clinicians at the institute
- Worked as a teaching assistant for biostatistics curriculum at Lerner College of Medicine

### **Skills**

**Programming:** R / Python / MySQL / SAS / Perl / JMP

**Relevant Modules:** scikit-learn / scipy / mglearn / pillow/ nltk / spacy / numpy / pandas /

matplotlib

**Operating system**: Windows / Linux / Mac OS **Languages**: English (proficient), Chinese (native)

Version Control: Git

## **Publications**

Cao, S., Wang, J. R., Ji, S., Yang, P., **Chen, J.**, Montierth, M. D., ... & Livingstone, J. (2020). Differing total mRNA expression shapes the molecular and clinical phenotype of cancer. *bioRxiv*.

Shin, S. J., Dodd-Eaton, E. B., Peng, G., Bojadzieva, J., **Chen, J.**, Amos, C. I., ... & Ballinger, M. L. (2020). Penetrance of Different Cancer Types in Families with Li-Fraumeni Syndrome: A Validation Study Using Multicenter Cohorts. *Cancer research*, 80(2), 354-360.

Shin, S. J., Dodd-Eaton, E. B., Gao, F., Bojadzieva, J., **Chen, J.**, Kong, X., ... & Wang, W. (2020). Penetrance estimates over time to first and second primary cancer diagnosis in families with Li-Fraumeni syndrome: a single institution perspective. *Cancer research*, 80(2), 347-353.

- Ilyas, H., Golubovsky, J. L., **Chen, J.**, Winkelman, R. D., Mroz, T. E., & Steinmetz, M. P. (2019). Risk factors for 90-day reoperation and readmission after lumbar surgery for lumbar spinal stenosis. *Journal of Neurosurgery: Spine*, 31(1), 20-26.
- Cao, S., Wang, Z., Gao, F., **Chen, J.**, Zhang, F., Frigo, D. E., ... & Wang, W. (2019). An R Implementation of Tumor-Stroma-Immune Transcriptome Deconvolution Pipeline using DeMixT. *bioRxiv*, 566075.

Golubovsky, J. L., Ilyas, H., **Chen, J.,** Tanenbaum, J. E., Mroz, T. E., & Steinmetz, M. P. (2018). Risk factors and associated complications for postoperative urinary retention after lumbar surgery for lumbar spinal stenosis. *The Spine Journal*, 18(9), 1533-1539.

## **Presentations & Posters**

- "Deconvolution reveals cell-type-specific transcriptional effects across cancer types," iBright, Houston, 2019
- "LFSPRO: A risk prediction R package for probabilities of age-of-onset of multiple primary cancers and specific cancer types in families with Li-Fraumeni Syndrome," ASHG, Houston, 2019
- "Deconvolution analysis to understand the tumor-stroma-immune environment in prostate cancer," Q-bio, Houston, 2019